<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Apache Drill - Schema-free SQL for Hadoop, NoSQL and Cloud Storage</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 11:18:15 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 11:18:15 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.13 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.13.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ability-to-run-drill-under-yarn-(drill-1170)&quot;&gt;Ability to Run Drill Under YARN (DRILL-1170)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can run Drill as a YARN application (&lt;a href=&quot;/docs/drill-on-yarn/&quot;&gt;Drill-on-YARN&lt;/a&gt;) if you want Drill to work alongside other applications, such as Hadoop and Spark, in a YARN-managed cluster. YARN assigns resources, such as memory and CPU, to applications in the cluster and eliminates the manual steps associated with installation and resource allocation for stand-alone applications in a multi-tenant environment. YARN automatically deploys (localizes) the Drill software onto each Drill node and manages the Drill cluster. Drill becomes a long-running application with YARN. You can monitor the Drill-on-YARN cluster using the Application Master web UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spnego-support-(drill-5425)&quot;&gt;SPNEGO Support (DRILL-5425)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use SPNEGO to extend Kerberos authentication to Web applications through HTTP. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sql-syntax-support-(drill-5868)&quot;&gt;SQL Syntax Support (DRILL-5868)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Query syntax appears highlighted in the Drill Web Console. In addition to syntax highlighting, auto-complete is supported in all SQL editors, including the Edit Query tab within an existing profile to rerun the query. For browsers like Chrome, you can type Ctrl+Space for a drop-down list and then use arrow keys for navigating through options. An auto-complete feature that specifies Drill keywords and functions, and the ability to write SQL from templates using snippets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user/distribution-specific-configuration-checks-during-startup-(drill-5741)&quot;&gt;User/Distribution-Specific Configuration Checks During Startup (DRILL-5741)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can define the maximum amount of cumulative memory allocated to the Drill process during startup through the &lt;code&gt;DRILLBIT_MAX_PROC_MEM&lt;/code&gt; environment variable. For example, if you set &lt;code&gt;DRILLBIT_MAX_PROC_MEM to 40G&lt;/code&gt;, the total amount of memory allocated to the following memory parameters cannot exceed 40G:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;DRILL_HEAP=8G&lt;/code&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;DRILL_MAX_DIRECT_MEMORY=10G&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;DRILLBIT_CODE_CACHE_SIZE=1024M&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At startup, an auto-setup.sh script performs a check to see if these memory parameters are declared. If the parameters are declared, the script performs a check to verify that the cumulative memory of the parameters does not exceed the value specified by &lt;code&gt;DRILLBIT_MAX_PROC_MEM&lt;/code&gt;. If the cumulative memory exceeds the total amount of memory defined by &lt;code&gt;DRILLBIT_MAX_PROC_MEM&lt;/code&gt;, Drill returns an error message with instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find a complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.13.0 release &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/apache-drill-1-13-0-release-notes/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2018/03/18/drill-1.13-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2018/03/18/drill-1.13-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Running SQL Queries on Amazon S3</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The functionality and sheer usefulness of Drill is growing fast.  If you&amp;#39;re a user of some of the popular BI tools out there like Tableau or SAP Lumira, now is a good time to take a look at how Drill can make your life easier, especially if  you&amp;#39;re faced with the task of quickly getting a handle on large sets of unstructured data.  With schema generated on the fly, you can save a lot of time and headaches by running SQL queries on the data where it rests without knowing much about columns or formats.  There&amp;#39;s even more good news:  Drill also works with data stored in the cloud.  With a few simple steps, you can configure the S3 storage plugin for Drill and be off to the races running queries.  In this post we&amp;#39;ll look at how to configure Drill to access data stored in an S3 bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re more of a visual person, you can skip this article entirely and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w8gZ2nn_ZUQ&quot;&gt;go straight to a video&lt;/a&gt; I put together that walks through an end-to-end example with Tableau.  This example is easily extended to other BI tools, as the steps are identical on the Drill side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a high level, configuring Drill to access S3 bucket data is accomplished with the following steps on each node running a drillbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download and install the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jets3t.org/&quot;&gt;JetS3t&lt;/a&gt; JAR files and enable them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add your S3 credentials in the relevant XML configuration file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure and enable the S3 storage plugin through the Drill web interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect your BI tool of choice and query away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consult the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/DRILL/Architectural+Overview&quot;&gt;Architectural Overview&lt;/a&gt; for a refresher on the architecture of Drill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps assume you have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/DRILL/Apache+Drill+in+10+Minutes&quot;&gt;typical Drill cluster and ZooKeeper quorum&lt;/a&gt; configured and running.  To access data in S3, you will need an S3 bucket configured and have the required Amazon security credentials in your possession.  An &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.aws.amazon.com/security/post/Tx1R9KDN9ISZ0HF/Where-s-my-secret-access-key&quot;&gt;Amazon blog post&lt;/a&gt; has more information on how to get these from your account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;configuration-steps&quot;&gt;Configuration Steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To connect Drill to S3, all of the drillbit nodes will need to access code in the JetS3t library developed by Amazon.  As of this writing, 0.9.2 is the latest version but you might want to check &lt;a href=&quot;https://jets3t.s3.amazonaws.com/toolkit/toolkit.html&quot;&gt;the main page&lt;/a&gt; to see if anything has been updated.  Be sure to get version 0.9.2 or later as earlier versions have a bug relating to reading Parquet data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;wget http://bitbucket.org/jmurty/jets3t/downloads/jets3t-0.9.2.zip
cp jets3t-0.9.2/jars/jets3t-0.9.2.jar &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$DRILL_HOME&lt;/span&gt;/jars/3rdparty
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, enable the plugin by editing the file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$DRILL_HOME&lt;/span&gt;/bin/hadoop_excludes.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and removing the line &lt;code&gt;jets3t&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill will need to know your S3 credentials in order to access data there. These credentials will need to be placed in the core-site.xml file for your installation.  If you already have a core-site.xml file configured for your environment, add the following parameters to it, otherwise create the file from scratch.  If you do end up creating it from scratch you will need to wrap these parameters with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;configuration&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/configuration&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot; data-lang=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;property&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;fs.s3.awsAccessKeyId&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;value&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;ID&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/property&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;property&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;fs.s3.awsSecretAccessKey&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;value&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;SECRET&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/property&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;property&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;fs.s3n.awsAccessKeyId&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;value&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;ID&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/property&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;property&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;fs.s3n.awsSecretAccessKey&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;value&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;SECRET&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/property&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps so far give Drill enough information to connect to the S3 service.  Remember, you have to do this on all the nodes running drillbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, let&amp;#39;s go into the Drill web interface and enable the S3 storage plugin.  In this case you only need to connect to &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt; of the nodes because Drill&amp;#39;s configuration is synchronized across the cluster.  Complete the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point your browser to &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;host&amp;gt;:8047&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the &amp;#39;Storage&amp;#39; tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good starting configuration for S3 can be entirely the same as the &lt;code&gt;dfs&lt;/code&gt; plugin, except the connection parameter is changed to &lt;code&gt;s3://bucket&lt;/code&gt;.  So first select the &lt;code&gt;Update&lt;/code&gt; button for &lt;code&gt;dfs&lt;/code&gt;, then select the text area and copy it into the clipboard (on Windows, ctrl-A, ctrl-C works).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Back&lt;/code&gt;, then create a new plugin by typing the name into the &lt;code&gt;New Storage Plugin&lt;/code&gt;, then press &lt;code&gt;Create&lt;/code&gt;.  You can choose any name, but a good convention is to use &lt;code&gt;s3-&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; so you can easily identify it later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the configuration area, paste the configuration you just grabbed from &amp;#39;dfs&amp;#39;.  Change the line &lt;code&gt;connection: &amp;quot;file:///&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;connection: &amp;quot;s3://&amp;lt;bucket&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;Update&lt;/code&gt;.  You should see a message that indicates success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point you can run queries on the data directly and you have a couple of options on how you want to access it.  You can use Drill Explorer and create a custom view (based on an SQL query) that you can then access in Tableau or other BI tools, or just use Drill directly from within the tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may want to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jNUsprJNQUg&quot;&gt;Tableau demo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With just a few lines of configuration, you&amp;#39;ve just opened the vast world of data available in the Amazon cloud and reduced the amount of work you have to do in advance to access data stored there with SQL.  There are even some &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/datasets&quot;&gt;public datasets&lt;/a&gt; available directly on S3 that are great for experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Drilling!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 00:16:07 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2018/02/09/running-sql-queries-on-amazon-s3/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2018/02/09/running-sql-queries-on-amazon-s3/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.12 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.12.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kafka-and-opentsdb-storage-plugins-(drill-4779,-drill-5337)&quot;&gt;Kafka and OpenTSDB Storage Plugins (DRILL-4779, DRILL-5337)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can configure Kafka and OpenTSDB as Drill data sources.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For Kafka storage plugin information, see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/drill/blob/master/contrib/storage-kafka/README.md&quot;&gt;README&lt;/a&gt; file. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For OpenTSDB storage plugin information, see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/drill/blob/master/contrib/storage-opentsdb/README.md&quot;&gt;README&lt;/a&gt; file. Configure the OpenTSDB storage plugin in the Storage tab of the Drill Web Console, as shown:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;{
 &amp;quot;storage&amp;quot;: {
   openTSDB: {
     type: &amp;quot;openTSDB&amp;quot;,
     connection: &amp;quot;http://localhost:10000&amp;quot;,
     enabled: false
      }
   }
 }   
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;queue-based-memory-assignment-for-buffering-operators-(throttling)-(drill-5716)&quot;&gt;Queue-Based Memory Assignment for Buffering Operators (Throttling) (DRILL-5716)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throttling limits the number of concurrent queries that run to prevent queries from failing with out-of-memory errors. When you enable throttling, you configure the number of concurrent queries that can run and the resource requirements for each query. Drill calculates the amount of memory to assign per query per node. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/throttling/&quot;&gt;Throttling&lt;/a&gt; for more information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;networking-functions&quot;&gt;Networking Functions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill supports the following networking functions to facilitate network analysis using Drill:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;inet_aton(&amp;lt;ip&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;: Converts an IPv4 address into an integer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;inet_ntoa( &amp;lt;int&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;: Converts an integer IP into dotted decimal notation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;in_network( &amp;lt;ip&amp;gt;,&amp;lt;cidr&amp;gt; )&lt;/code&gt;: Returns true if the IP address is in the given CIDR block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;address_count( &amp;lt;cidr&amp;gt; )&lt;/code&gt;: Returns the number of IPs in a given CIDR block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;broadcast_address( &amp;lt;cidr&amp;gt; )&lt;/code&gt;: Returns the broadcast address for a given CIDR block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;netmask(&amp;lt;cidr&amp;gt; )&lt;/code&gt;: Returns the netmask for a given CIDR block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;low_address(&amp;lt;cidr&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;: Returns the first address in a given CIDR block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;high_address(&amp;lt;cidr&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;: Returns the last address in a given CIDR block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;url_encode( &amp;lt;url&amp;gt; )&lt;/code&gt;: Returns a URL encoded string&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;url_decode( &amp;lt;url&amp;gt; )&lt;/code&gt;: Decodes ``a URL encoded string&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;is_valid_IP(&amp;lt;ip&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;: Returns true if the IP is a valid IP address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;is_private_ip(&amp;lt;ip&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;: Returns true if the IP is a private IPv4 address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;is_valid_IPv4(&amp;lt;ip&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;: Returns true if the IP is a valid IPv4 address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;is_valid_IPv6(&amp;lt;ip&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;: Returns true if the IP is a valid IPv6 address&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ssl-support&quot;&gt;SSL Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill supports SSL to encrypt data passed between the Drill client and Drillbit. SSL also provides one-way authentication through which the Drill client verifies the identity of the Drillbit. The SASL feature in Drill provides authentication and an option to encrypt data, however the encryption feature is not available when using Plain authentication. If you need to use Plain authentication (certain BI tools only use Plain authentication), you can enable SSL to encrypt data. You can have both SASL and SSL enabled when using Plain authentication only. For any other scenario, using SSL and SASL encryption together is strongly discouraged. The Drill server requires an SSL certificate. The certificate can be self-signed or signed by a CA (Certificate Authority). SSL is not supported for communication between Drillbits.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;network-encryption-support&quot;&gt;Network Encryption Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill 1.10 provided authentication support through Plain and Kerberos authentication mechanisms to authenticate the Drill client to Drillbit and Drillbit to Drillbit communication channels. Drill 1.11 extends that support to include encryption. Drill uses the Kerberos mechanism over the SASL framework to encrypt the communication channels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;access-to-paths-outside-the-current-workspace-(drill-5964)&quot;&gt;Access to Paths Outside the Current Workspace (DRILL-5964)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new parameter, allowAccessOutsideWorkspace, in the dfs storage plugin configuration prevents users from accessing paths outside the root of a workspace. The default value for the parameter is false. Set the parameter to true to allow users access outside of a workspace. If existing storage plugin configurations do not specify the parameter, users cannot access paths outside the configured workspaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find a complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.12.0 release &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=12341087&amp;amp;styleName=Html&amp;amp;projectId=12313820&amp;amp;Create=Create&amp;amp;atl_token=A5KQ-2QAV-T4JA-FDED%7Cd194b12b906cd370f36d15e8af60a94592b89038%7Clin&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2017/12/15/drill-1.12-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2017/12/15/drill-1.12-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.11 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.11.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cryptography-related-functions-(drill-5634)&quot;&gt;Cryptography-Related Functions (DRILL-5634)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill provides the following cryptographic-related functions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aes_encrypt()&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aes_decrypt()&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;md5()&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sha()&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sha1()&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sha2()&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spill-to-disk-for-hash-aggregate-operator-(drill-5457)&quot;&gt;Spill to Disk for Hash Aggregate Operator (DRILL-5457)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hash aggregate operator can spill data to disk in cases where the operation exceeds the set memory limit. Note that you may need to increase the default value of the &lt;code&gt;planner.memory.max_query_memory_per_node&lt;/code&gt; option due to insufficient memory.      &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;format-plugin-support-for-pcap-files-(drill-5432)&quot;&gt;Format Plugin Support for PCAP Files (DRILL-5432)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “pcap” format plugin enables Drill to read PCAP files. You must add the “pcap” format to the dfs storage plugin configuration, as shown:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;   &amp;quot;pcap&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;pcap&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;extensions&amp;quot;: [
            &amp;quot;pcap&amp;quot;
          ]
        }   
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;change-the-hdfs-block-size-for-parquet-files-(drill-5379)&quot;&gt;Change the HDFS Block Size for Parquet Files (DRILL-5379)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;store.parquet.writer.use_single_fs_block&lt;/code&gt; option enables Drill to write a Parquet file as a single file system block without changing the file system default block size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;store-query-profiles-in-memory-(drill-5481)&quot;&gt;Store Query Profiles in Memory (DRILL-5481)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;drill.exec.profiles.store.inmemory&lt;/code&gt; option enables Drill to store query profiles in memory instead of writing the query profiles to disk. The &lt;code&gt;drill.exec.profiles.store.capacity&lt;/code&gt; option sets the maximum number of most recent profiles to retain in memory.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;configurable-ctas-directory-and-file-permissions-option-(drill-5391)&quot;&gt;Configurable CTAS Directory and File Permissions Option (DRILL-5391)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use the &lt;code&gt;exec.persistent_table.umask&lt;/code&gt; configuration option, at the system or session level, to modify permissions on directories and files that result from running the CTAS command. By default, the option is set to 002, which sets the default directory permissions to 775 and default file permissions to 664.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;support-for-network-encryption-(drill-4335)&quot;&gt;Support for Network Encryption (DRILL-4335)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill can use SASL to support network encryption between the Drill client and drillbits, and also between drillbits.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;metadata-file-stores-relative-paths-(drill-3867)&quot;&gt;Metadata file Stores Relative Paths (DRILL-3867)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now stores the relative path in the metadata file (versus the absolute path), which enables you to move partitioned Parquet directories from one location in DFS to another without having to rebuild the Parquet metadata files; the metadata remains valid in the new location.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;support-for-additional-quoting-identifiers-(drill-3510)&quot;&gt;Support for Additional Quoting Identifiers (DRILL-3510)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to back ticks, the SQL parser in Drill can use double quotes and square brackets as identifier quotes. Use the &lt;code&gt;planner.parser.quoting_identifiers&lt;/code&gt; configuration option, at the system or session level, to set the type of identifier quotes that the SQL parser in Drill uses, as shown:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;   ALTER SESSION SET planner.parser.quoting_identifiers = &amp;#39;&amp;quot;&amp;#39;;  
   ALTER SESSION SET planner.parser.quoting_identifiers = &amp;#39;[&amp;#39;;  
   ALTER SESSION SET planner.parser.quoting_identifiers = &amp;#39;`&amp;#39;;  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default setting is back ticks. The quoting identifier used in queries must match the setting. If you use another type of quoting identifier, Drill returns an error.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find a complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.11.0 release &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?projectId=12313820&amp;amp;version=12339943&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2017/07/31/drill-1.11-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2017/07/31/drill-1.11-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.10 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.10.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cttas&quot;&gt;CTTAS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CREATE TEMPORARY TABLE AS (CTTAS) command stores the results of a query in a temporary table. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/create-temporary-table-as-cttas/&quot;&gt;CTTAS&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;improved-fault-tolerance&quot;&gt;Improved Fault Tolerance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An optional &lt;code&gt;tries=&amp;lt;value&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; parameter included in the JDBC connection string indicates the number of unique drillbits to which the client can try to connect. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/using-the-jdbc-driver/#using-the-jdbc-url-format-for-a-direct-drillbit-connection&quot;&gt;Using the JDBC URL Format for a Direct Drillbit Connection&lt;/a&gt;.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drill-version-and-statistics-in-web-console&quot;&gt;Drill Version and Statistics in Web Console&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Web Console displays additional query profile statistics and the Drill version running on each Drill node in the cluster. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/identifying-multiple-drill-versions-in-a-cluster&quot;&gt;Identifying Multiple Drill Versions in a Cluster&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implicit-interpretation-of-int96&quot;&gt;Implicit Interpretation of INT96&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill implicitly interprets the INT96 timestamp data type in Parquet files when the new &lt;code&gt;store.parquet.reader.int96_as_timestamp&lt;/code&gt; option is enabled. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/parquet-format/#about-int96-support&quot;&gt;About INT96 Support&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kerberos-authentication&quot;&gt;Kerberos Authentication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill supports Kerberos authentication between the client and drillbit. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/configuring-kerberos-authentication/&quot;&gt;Configuring Kerberos Authentication&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/securing-drill/&quot;&gt;Securing Drill&lt;/a&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.10.0 release can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=12338769&amp;amp;styleName=Html&amp;amp;projectId=12313820&amp;amp;Create=Create&amp;amp;atl_token=A5KQ-2QAV-T4JA-FDED%7C264858c85b35c3b8ac66b0573aa7e88ffa802c9d%7Clin&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2017/03/15/drill-1.10-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2017/03/15/drill-1.10-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.9 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.9.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;asynchronous-parquet-reader&quot;&gt;Asynchronous Parquet Reader&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new asynchronous Parquet reader feature improves the performance of the Parquet Scan operator by increasing the speed at which the Parquet reader scans, decompresses, and decodes data. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/asynchronous-parquet-reader/&quot;&gt;Asynchronous Parquet Reader&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parquet-filter-pushdown&quot;&gt;Parquet Filter Pushdown&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Parquet filter pushdown feature optimizes Drill’s performance by pruning extraneous data from a Parquet file to reduce the amount of data that Drill scans and reads when a query on a Parquet file contains a filter expression. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/parquet-filter-pushdown/&quot;&gt;Parquet Filter Pushdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dynamic-udf-support&quot;&gt;Dynamic UDF Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Dynamic UDF feature enables users to register and unregister UDFs on their own using the new CREATE FUNCTION USING JAR and DROP FUNCTION USING JAR commands. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/dynamic-udfs/&quot;&gt;Dynamic UDFs&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;httpd-format-plugin&quot;&gt;HTTPD Format Plugin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new HTTPD format plugin adds the capability to query HTTP web server logs natively and also includes parse_url() and parse_query() UDFs. The parse_url() UDF returns maps of the URL. The parse_query() UDF returns the query string.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.9.0 release can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=12337861&amp;amp;styleName=Html&amp;amp;projectId=12313820&amp;amp;Create=Create&amp;amp;atl_token=A5KQ-2QAV-T4JA-FDED%7Cedcc6294c1851bcd19a3686871e085181f755a91%7Clin&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2016/11/29/drill-1.9-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2016/11/29/drill-1.9-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.8 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.8.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;metadata-cache-pruning&quot;&gt;Metadata Cache Pruning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now applies partition pruning to the metadata cache file. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/partition-pruning-introduction/&quot;&gt;Partition Pruning Introduction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/optimizing-parquet-metadata-reading/&quot;&gt;Optimizing Parquet Metadata Reading&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-exists-support&quot;&gt;IF EXISTS Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can include the new IF EXISTS parameter with the DROP TABLE and DROP VIEW commands to prevent Drill from returning error messages when a table or view does not exist. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/drop-table/&quot;&gt;DROP TABLE&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/drop-view/&quot;&gt;DROP VIEW&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;describe-schema-command&quot;&gt;DESCRIBE SCHEMA Command&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now supports the DESCRIBE SCHEMA command which provides schema properties for storage plugin configurations and workspaces. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/describe/&quot;&gt;DESCRIBE&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multi-byte-delimiter-support&quot;&gt;Multi-Byte Delimiter Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now supports multi-byte delimiters for text files, such as \r\n. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/plugin-configuration-basics/#list-of-attributes-and-definitions&quot;&gt;List of Attributes and Definitions&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;filter-selectivity-estimate-parameters&quot;&gt;Filter Selectivity Estimate Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New parameters set the minimum filter selectivity estimate to increase the parallelization of the major fragment performing a join. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/configuration-options-introduction/#system-options&quot;&gt;System Options&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.8.0 release can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=12334768&amp;amp;styleName=Html&amp;amp;projectId=12313820&amp;amp;Create=Create&amp;amp;atl_token=A5KQ-2QAV-T4JA-FDED%7Ce8d020149d9a6082481af301e563adbe35c76a87%7Clout&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2016/08/30/drill-1.8-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2016/08/30/drill-1.8-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.7 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.7.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monitoring-via-jmx&quot;&gt;Monitoring via JMX&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can access Drill system-level metrics, collected by JMX, through the Metrics page in the Drill Web Console or a remote JMX monitoring tool. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/monitoring-metrics/&quot;&gt;Monitoring Metrics&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hive-char-data-type&quot;&gt;Hive CHAR Data Type&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill automatically converts the Hive CHAR data type to VARCHAR. You no longer need to cast the Hive CHAR data type to VARCHAR when you query Hive tables. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/hive-to-drill-data-type-mapping/&quot;&gt;Hive-to-Drill Data Type Mapping&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hbase&quot;&gt;HBase&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now supports HBase 1.x. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.7.0 release can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=12334767&amp;amp;styleName=&amp;amp;projectId=12313820&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2016/06/28/drill-1.7-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2016/06/28/drill-1.7-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.6 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.6.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inbound-impersonation&quot;&gt;Inbound Impersonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feature is useful in a multi-tier architecture where queries must run as the end user instead of the application user. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/configuring-inbound-impersonation/&quot;&gt;Configuring Inbound Impersonation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;additional-custom-window-frames&quot;&gt;Additional Custom Window Frames&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The window function frame clause now supports additional custom frames. See &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/sql-window-functions-introduction/#syntax&quot;&gt;Window Function Syntax&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.6.0 release can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=12334766&amp;amp;styleName=Html&amp;amp;projectId=12313820&amp;amp;Create=Create&amp;amp;atl_token=A5KQ-2QAV-T4JA-FDED%7C9ec2112379f0ae5d2b67a8cbd2626bcde62b41cd%7Clout&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2016/03/16/drill-1.6-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2016/03/16/drill-1.6-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.5 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 1.5.0. You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release provides the following bug fixes and improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-authentication&quot;&gt;Web Authentication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill 1.5 extends Drill user authentication to the Web Console and underlying REST API so administrators can control the extent of access to the Web Console and REST API client applications. Configuration docs are available &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/configuring-web-console-and-rest-api-security/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kudu-support&quot;&gt;Kudu Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now includes experimental support for querying the Apache Kudu (incubating) scalable columnar database.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;improved-memory-allocator&quot;&gt;Improved Memory Allocator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill uses a new allocator that improves an operator’s use of direct memory and tracks the memory use more accurately. See the &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/configuring-drill-memory/&quot;&gt;Configuring Drill Memory&lt;/a&gt; doc page for more info.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;configurable-caching-of-hive-metadata&quot;&gt;Configurable Caching of Hive Metadata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now configure the TTL for the Hive metadata client cache depending on how frequently the Hive metadata is updated. See the &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/hive-metadata-caching/&quot;&gt;Hive Metadata Caching&lt;/a&gt; doc page for more info.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A complete list of JIRAs resolved in the 1.5.0 release can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?projectId=12313820&amp;amp;version=12332948&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2016/02/16/drill-1.5-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2016/02/16/drill-1.5-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
