<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Apache Drill - Schema-free SQL for Hadoop, NoSQL and Cloud Storage</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 15:48:20 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 15:48:20 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill Tutorial at NoSQL Now! 2015</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//addthisevent.com/libs/1.5.8/ate.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2015/07/23/drill-tutorial-at-nosql-now-2015/&quot; title=&quot;Add to Calendar&quot; class=&quot;addthisevent&quot;&gt;
    Add to Calendar
    &lt;span class=&quot;_start&quot;&gt;08-20-2015 13:00:00&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_end&quot;&gt;08-20-2014 16:15:00&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_zonecode&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_summary&quot;&gt;Drill Tutorial at NoSQL Now! 2015&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_description&quot;&gt;NoSQL Now! 2015 is hosting a 3-hour tutorial on Apache Drill. Drill committers Tomer Shiran and Jacques Nadeau will demonstrate how to analyze NoSQL data with SQL queries and standard BI tools.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_location&quot;&gt;San Jose Convention Center, 150 West San Carlos St, San Jose, CA 95113 USA&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_organizer&quot;&gt;Tomer Shiran&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_organizer_email&quot;&gt;tshiran\@apache.org&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_all_day_event&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;_date_format&quot;&gt;MM-DD-YYYY&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NoSQL Now! 2015 will be hosting a &lt;a href=&quot;http://nosql2015.dataversity.net/sessionPop.cfm?confid=90&amp;amp;proposalid=7727&quot;&gt;3-hour tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on Apache Drill. Jacques Nadeau and I will provide a deep dive on Drill and demonstrate how to analyze NoSQL data with SQL queries and standard BI tools. We would love to see you there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you &lt;a href=&quot;http://nosql2015.dataversity.net/reg.cfm&quot;&gt;register&lt;/a&gt;, use the coupon code &amp;quot;SPEAKER&amp;quot; for a 20% discount on the registration fees.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/07/23/drill-tutorial-at-nosql-now-2015/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/07/23/drill-tutorial-at-nosql-now-2015/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.1 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#39;m happy to announce the availability of the Drill 1.1 release. This release addresses &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?projectId=12313820&amp;amp;version=12329689&quot;&gt;162 JIRAs&lt;/a&gt; on top of May&amp;#39;s 1.0 release. Highlights include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;automatic-partitioning-for-parquet-files&quot;&gt;Automatic Partitioning for Parquet Files&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now supports creating partitions automatically when using &lt;code&gt;CREATE TABLE AS&lt;/code&gt; (CTAS) to generate Parquet files. By leveraging the unique capabilities of the Parquet file format, Drill is able provide this capability and still maintain data integrity and compatibility with all other systems that consume Parquet (a world&amp;#39;s first). This functionality can be exercised by utilizing the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/partition-by-clause/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;PARTITION BY&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; clause support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;window-functions&quot;&gt;Window Functions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now has first-class support for SQL window Functions. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aggregate Functions: &lt;code&gt;AVG&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;COUNT&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;MAX&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;MIN&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;SUM&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ranking Functions: &lt;code&gt;CUME_DIST&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;DENSE_RANK&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;PERCENT_RANK&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;RANK&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ROW_NUMBER&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community has done an excellent job providing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/sql-window-functions-introduction/&quot;&gt;comprehensive documentation&lt;/a&gt; so that you can start using window functions immediately.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hive-storage-plugin-enhancements&quot;&gt;Hive Storage Plugin Enhancements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ve enhanced Drill to work even better with Hive. We started by upgrading Drill&amp;#39;s support to work with Hive 1.0. In addition, Drill now provides a powerful new security feature called &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/configuring-user-impersonation-with-hive-authorization/&quot;&gt;delegated Hive impersonation&lt;/a&gt;. Compatibility and performance are also improved with better data type support (including support for binary, tinyint and smallint data types) and better concurrency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sql-union-improvements&quot;&gt;SQL UNION Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ve enhanced support for SQL &lt;code&gt;UNION&lt;/code&gt; functionality.  Drill now supports both &lt;code&gt;UNION&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;UNION ALL&lt;/code&gt; capabilities.  We&amp;#39;ve also improved the query optimizer to better optimize plans that include the &lt;code&gt;UNION&lt;/code&gt; clause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-features-for-complex-data&quot;&gt;New Features For Complex Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill&amp;#39;s complex data capabilities continue to be the best in the market, now including support for &lt;code&gt;COUNT&lt;/code&gt; aggregations on various types of complex objects. Also, Drill&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;FLATTEN&lt;/code&gt; function now supports very large complex objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;improved-jdbc-driver-compatibility&quot;&gt;Improved JDBC Driver Compatibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apache Drill&amp;#39;s JDBC driver continues to improve. This includes a number of enhancements and fixes to better support JDBC tools including &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/using-microstrategy-analytics-with-apache-drill/&quot;&gt;MicroStrategy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/using-tibco-spotfire-desktop-with-drill/&quot;&gt;TIBCO Spotfire&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/configuring-jreport-with-drill/&quot;&gt;JReport&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/using-jdbc-with-squirrel-on-windows/&quot;&gt;SQuirreL&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Apache Drill community now publishes the JDBC driver for easy inclusion in your application through the use of Maven coordinates. You can incorporate Drill&amp;#39;s JDBC driver into your application by &lt;a href=&quot;http://search.maven.org/remotecontent?filepath=org/apache/drill/exec/drill-jdbc-all/1.1.0/drill-jdbc-all-1.1.0.jar&quot;&gt;downloading it directly&lt;/a&gt; or referencing the following coordinates within your Maven application.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;dependency&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;groupId&amp;gt;org.apache.drill.exec&amp;lt;/groupId&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;artifactId&amp;gt;drill-jdbc-all&amp;lt;/artifactId&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;version&amp;gt;1.1.0&amp;lt;/version&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dependency&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mongodb-3.0-support&quot;&gt;MongoDB 3.0 Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill now uses MongoDB&amp;#39;s latest Java driver and has enhanced connection pooling for better performance and resilience in large-scale deployments.  Learn more about using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/docs/mongodb-plugin-for-apache-drill/&quot;&gt;MongoDB plugin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;many-more-fixes&quot;&gt;Many More Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill includes a variety of &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?projectId=12313820&amp;amp;version=12329689&quot;&gt;other fixes and enhancements&lt;/a&gt; including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvements for certain types of exists and correlated subqueries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixes for running Drill on Windows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvements in implicit casting capabilities in schemaless scenarios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvements in &lt;code&gt;INFORMATION_SCHEMA&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixes for the Web UI and the REST API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-frequent-releases&quot;&gt;More Frequent Releases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amazing Drill community continues to be the driving force behind these rapid iterative releases.  Thanks to all the &lt;a href=&quot;/team/&quot;&gt;committers&lt;/a&gt; and contributors that made this release possible!  The community&amp;#39;s goal continues to be maintaining a 4-6 release cycle throughout the summer.  This means you will have many more enhancements to look for in the next few months.  If you use Drill, want to, or want to help develop it, drop by in &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/mailinglists/&quot;&gt;the community&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the &lt;a href=&quot;https://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;Drill 1.1.0 release&lt;/a&gt; now and let us know your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drill On!&lt;br&gt;
Jacques Nadeau&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/07/05/drill-1.1-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/07/05/drill-1.1-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Apache Software Foundation Announces Apache Drill 1.0</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thousands of users adopt Open Source, enterprise-grade, schema-free SQL query engine for Apache Hadoop®, NoSQL and Cloud storage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forest Hill, MD --19 May 2015-- The Apache Software Foundation (ASF), the all-volunteer developers, stewards, and incubators of more than 350 Open Source projects and initiatives, announced today the availability of Apache™ Drill™ 1.0, the schema-free SQL query engine for Apache Hadoop®, NoSQL and Cloud storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The production-ready 1.0 release represents a significant milestone for the Drill project,&amp;quot; said Tomer Shiran, member of the Apache Drill Project Management Committee. &amp;quot;It is the outcome of almost three years of development involving dozens of engineers from numerous companies. Apache Drill&amp;#39;s flexibility and ease-of-use have attracted thousands of users, and the enterprise-grade reliability, security and performance in the 1.0 release will further accelerate adoption.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exponential growth of data in recent years, and the shift towards rapid application development, new data is increasingly being stored in non-relational, schema-free datastores including Hadoop, NoSQL and Cloud storage. Apache Drill revolutionizes data exploration and analytics by enabling analysts, business users, data scientists and developers to explore and analyze this data without sacrificing the flexibility and agility offered by these datastores. Drill processes the data in-situ without requiring users to define schemas or transform data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Drill introduces the JSON document model to the world of SQL-based analytics and BI&amp;quot; said Jacques Nadeau, Vice President of Apache Drill. &amp;quot;This enables users to query fixed-schema, evolving-schema and schema-free data stored in a variety of formats and datastores. The architecture of relational query engines and databases is built on the assumption that all data has a simple and static structure that’s known in advance, and this 40-year-old assumption is simply no longer valid. We designed Drill from the ground up to address the new reality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apache Drill&amp;#39;s architecture is unique in many ways. It is the only columnar execution engine that supports complex and schema-free data, and the only execution engine that performs data-driven query compilation (and re-compilation, also known as schema discovery) during query execution. These unique capabilities enable Drill to achieve record-breaking performance with the flexibility offered by the JSON document model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business intelligence (BI) partner ecosystem is embracing the power of Apache Drill. Organizations such as Information Builders, JReport (Jinfonet Software), MicroStrategy, Qlik®, Simba, Tableau, and TIBCO, are working closely with the Drill community to interoperate BI tools with Drill through standard ODBC and JDBC connectivity. This collaboration enables end users to explore data by leveraging sophisticated visualization tools and advanced analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;We&amp;#39;ve been using Apache Drill for the past six months,&amp;quot; said Andrew Hamilton, CTO of Cardlytics. &amp;quot;Its ease of deployment and use along with its ability to quickly process trillions of records has made it an invaluable tool inside Cardlytics. Queries that were previously insurmountable are now common occurrence. Congratulations to the Drill community on this momentous occasion.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Drill&amp;#39;s columnar execution engine and optimizer take full advantage of Apache Parquet&amp;#39;s columnar storage to achieve maximum performance,&amp;quot; said Julien Le Dem, Technical Lead of Analytics Data Pipeline at Twitter and Vice President of Apache Parquet. &amp;quot;The Drill team has been a key contributor to the Parquet project, including recent enhancements to Parquet types and vectorization. The Drill team’s involvement in the Parquet community is instrumental in driving the standard.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Apache Drill 1.0 raises the bar for secure, reliable and scalable SQL-on-Hadoop,&amp;quot; said Piyush Bhargava, distinguished engineer, IT, Cisco Systems. &amp;quot;Because Drill integrates with existing data virtualization and visualization tools, we expect it will improve adoption of self-service data exploration and large-scale BI queries on our advanced Hadoop platform at Cisco.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;MicroStrategy recognized early on the value of Apache Drill and is one of the first analytic platforms to certify Drill,&amp;quot; said Tim Lang, senior executive vice president and chief technology officer at MicroStrategy Incorporated.  &amp;quot;Because Drill is designed to be used with a minimal learning curve, it opens up more complex data sets to the end user who can immediately visualize and analyze new information using MicroStrategy’s advanced capabilities.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Apache Drill closes a gap around self-service SQL queries in Hadoop, especially on complex, dynamic NoSQL data types,&amp;quot; said Mike Foster, Strategic Alliances Technology Officer at Qlik.  &amp;quot;Drill&amp;#39;s performance advantages for Hadoop data access, combined with the Qlik associative experience, enables our customers to continue discovering business value from a wide range of data. Congratulations to the Apache Drill community.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Apache Drill empowers people to access data that is traditionally difficult to work with,&amp;quot; said Jeff Feng, product manager, Tableau.  &amp;quot;Direct access within a centralized data repository and without pre-generating metadata definitions encourages data democracy which is essential for data-driven organizations. Additionally, Drill&amp;#39;s instant and secure access to complex data formats, such as JSON, opens up extended analytical opportunities.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Congratulations to the Apache Drill community on the availability of 1.0,&amp;quot; said Karl Van den Bergh, Vice President, Products and Cloud at TIBCO. &amp;quot;Drill promises to bring low-latency access to data stored in Hadoop and HBase via standard SQL semantics. This innovation is in line with the value of Fast Data analysis, which TIBCO customers welcome and appreciate.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The community&amp;#39;s accomplishment is a testament to The Apache Software Foundation&amp;#39;s ability to bring together diverse companies to work towards a common goal. None of this would have been possible without the contribution of engineers with advanced degrees and experience in relational databases, data warehousing, MPP, query optimization, Hadoop and NoSQL,&amp;quot; added Nadeau. &amp;quot;Our community&amp;#39;s strength is what will solidify Apache Drill as a key data technology for the next decade. We welcome interested individuals to learn more about Drill by joining the community&amp;#39;s mailing lists, attending upcoming talks by Drill code committers at various conferences including Hadoop Summit, NoSQL Now, Hadoop World, or at a local Apache Drill MeetUp.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Availability and Oversight
Apache Drill 1.0 is available immediately as a free download from &lt;a href=&quot;http://drill.apache.org/download/&quot;&gt;http://drill.apache.org/download/&lt;/a&gt;. Documentation is available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://drill.apache.org/docs/&quot;&gt;http://drill.apache.org/docs/&lt;/a&gt;. As with all Apache products, Apache Drill software is released under the Apache License v2.0, and is overseen by a self-selected team of active contributors to the project. A Project Management Committee (PMC) guides the project&amp;#39;s day-to-day operations, including community development and product releases. For ways to become involved with Apache Drill, visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://drill.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://drill.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; and @ApacheDrill on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About The Apache Software Foundation (ASF)
Established in 1999, the all-volunteer Foundation oversees more than 350 leading Open Source projects, including Apache HTTP Server --the world&amp;#39;s most popular Web server software. Through the ASF&amp;#39;s meritocratic process known as &amp;quot;The Apache Way,&amp;quot; more than 500 individual Members and 4,500 Committers successfully collaborate to develop freely available enterprise-grade software, benefiting millions of users worldwide: thousands of software solutions are distributed under the Apache License; and the community actively participates in ASF mailing lists, mentoring initiatives, and ApacheCon, the Foundation&amp;#39;s official user conference, trainings, and expo. The ASF is a US 501(c)(3) charitable organization, funded by individual donations and corporate sponsors including Bloomberg, Budget Direct, Cerner, Citrix, Cloudera, Comcast, Facebook, Google, Hortonworks, HP, IBM, InMotion Hosting, iSigma, Matt Mullenweg, Microsoft, Pivotal, Produban, WANdisco, and Yahoo. For more information, visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://www.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; or follow @TheASF on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© The Apache Software Foundation. &amp;quot;Apache&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Apache Drill&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Drill&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Apache Hadoop&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Hadoop&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Apache Parquet&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Parquet&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;ApacheCon&amp;quot;, are registered trademarks or trademarks of The Apache Software Foundation. All other brands and trademarks are the property of their respective owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;# # #&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/05/19/the-apache-software-foundation-announces-apache-drill-1.0/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/05/19/the-apache-software-foundation-announces-apache-drill-1.0/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 1.0 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We embarked on the Drill project in late 2012 with two primary objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable agility by getting rid of all the traditional overhead - namely, the need to load data, create and maintain schemas, transform data, etc. We wanted to develop a system that would support the speed and agility at which modern organizations want (or need) to operate in this era.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlock the data housed in non-relational datastores like NoSQL, Hadoop and cloud storage, making it available not only to developers, but also business users, analysts, data scientists and anyone else who can write a SQL query or use a BI tool. Non-relational datastores are capturing an increasing share of the world&amp;#39;s data, and it&amp;#39;s incredibly hard to explore and analyze this data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of the production-ready Drill 1.0 release. This release addresses &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?projectId=12313820&amp;amp;version=12325568&quot;&gt;228 JIRAs&lt;/a&gt; on top of the 0.9 release earlier this month. Highlights include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substantial improvements in stability, memory handling and performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvements in Drill CLI experience with addition of convenience shortcuts and improved colors/alignment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substantial additions to documentation including coverage of troubleshooting, performance tuning and many additions to the SQL reference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enhancements in join planning to facilitate high speed planning of large and complicated joins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add support for new context functions including &lt;code&gt;CURRENT_USER&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CURRENT_SCHEMA&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to treat all numbers as approximate decimals when reading JSON&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enhancements in Drill&amp;#39;s text and CSV handling to support first row skipping, configurable field/line delimiters and configurable quoting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved JDBC compatibility (and tracing proxy for easy debugging).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to do JDBC connections with direct urls (avoiding ZooKeeper)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic selection of spooling or back-pressure exchange semantics to avoid distributed deadlocks in complex sort-heavy queries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvements in query profile reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addition of &lt;code&gt;ILIKE(VARCHAR, PATTERN)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;SUBSTR(VARCHAR, REGEX)&lt;/code&gt; functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would not have been able to reach this milestone without the tremendous effort by all the &lt;a href=&quot;/team/&quot;&gt;committers&lt;/a&gt; and contributors, and we would like to congratulate the entire community on achieving this milestone. While 1.0 is an exciting milestone, it&amp;#39;s really just the beginning of the journey. We&amp;#39;ll release 1.1 next month, and continue with our 4-6 week release cycle, so you can count on many additional enhancements over the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also be sure to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2015/05/19/the-apache-software-foundation-announces-apache-drill-1.0/&quot;&gt;Apache Software Foundation&amp;#39;s press release&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Drilling!&lt;br&gt;
Tomer Shiran and Jacques Nadeau&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/05/19/drill-1.0-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/05/19/drill-1.0-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 0.9 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been about a month since the release of Drill 0.8, which included &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/drill-0.8-released/&quot;&gt;more than 240 improvements&lt;/a&gt;. Today we&amp;#39;re happy to announce the availability of Drill 0.9, providing additional enhancements and bug fixes. In fact, this release includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?projectId=12313820&amp;amp;version=12328813&quot;&gt;200 resolved JIRAs&lt;/a&gt;. Some of the noteworthy features in Drill 0.9 are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authentication&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-2674&quot;&gt;DRILL-2674&lt;/a&gt;). Drill now supports username/password authentication through the Java and C++ clients, as well as JDBC and ODBC. On the server-side, Drill leverages Linux PAM to securely validate the credentials. Users can choose to use an external user directory such as Active Directory or LDAP. To enable authentication, set the &lt;code&gt;security.user.auth&lt;/code&gt; option in &lt;code&gt;drill-override.conf&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impersonation&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-2363&quot;&gt;DRILL-2363&lt;/a&gt;). Queries now execute and access resources using the identity of the user who submitted the query. Previously, all queries would run as the same user (eg, &lt;code&gt;drill&lt;/code&gt;). With the new impersonation capability, the query will fail if the submitting user does not have permission to read the requested file(s) in the distributed file system. To enable impersonation, set the &lt;code&gt;drill.exec.impersonation&lt;/code&gt; option in &lt;code&gt;drill-override.conf&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ownership chaining&lt;/strong&gt;. Drill now allows views with different owners to be chained. This represents a very flexible access control solution. For example, an administrator with access to raw, sensitive data could create a view called &lt;code&gt;masked&lt;/code&gt; which would expose only a subset of the data to other users. The administrator would enable users to read the &lt;code&gt;masked&lt;/code&gt; view but not the raw data. Note that Drill provides an option &lt;code&gt;max_chained_user_hops&lt;/code&gt; that specifies how many ownership changed are allowed in a chain, thereby providing administrators (or data stewards) more control over sharing of data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB authentication&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-1502&quot;&gt;DRILL-1502&lt;/a&gt;). Drill can now connect to a MongoDB cluster that requires authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extended JSON datatypes&lt;/strong&gt;. Our friends at MongoDB invented &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.mongodb.org/manual/reference/mongodb-extended-json/&quot;&gt;extended JSON&lt;/a&gt; - a set of extensions to the JSON format for supporting additional data types. We decided to embrace extended JSON in Drill. For example, standard JSON doesn&amp;#39;t have a time type, so a time could be represented as either a string or a number: &lt;code&gt;{&amp;quot;foo&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;19:20:30.450Z&amp;quot;}&lt;/code&gt; is just a string. With extended JSON, the &lt;code&gt;$time&lt;/code&gt; qualifier can be used to specify that &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; is a time &lt;code&gt;{&amp;quot;foo&amp;quot;: {&amp;quot;$time&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;19:20:30.450Z&amp;quot;}}&lt;/code&gt;.
We now support a number of qualifiers including &lt;code&gt;$bin&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$date&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$time&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$interval&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$numberLong&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$dateDay&lt;/code&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/drill/blob/master/exec/java-exec/src/test/resources/vector/complex/extended.json&quot;&gt;the example&lt;/a&gt;). We&amp;#39;re in the process of adding some additional qualifiers to make sure that all of MongoDB&amp;#39;s extended types are supported (this is particularly important when querying data in MongoDB).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avro support&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-1512&quot;&gt;DRILL-1512&lt;/a&gt;). Drill can now read Avro files. This patch was contributed by Andrew Selden at Elastic.co (formerly known as Elasticsearch).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved error messages&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-2675&quot;&gt;DRILL-2675&lt;/a&gt; and more). It can be challenging for a complex distributed system like Drill to translate low-level internal conditions into actionable messages to the user. This release includes several enhancements that enable Drill to accomplish just that in a variety of cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parquet and Calcite enhancements&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-1410&quot;&gt;DRILL-1410&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-1384&quot;&gt;DRILL-1384&lt;/a&gt;). Drill isn&amp;#39;t a traditional query engine - it&amp;#39;s the first analytical query engine with a JSON data model. This has required us to enhance Parquet (our columnar format) and Calcite (our SQL parser). These enhancements have now been contributed back to those projects, and Drill is using the latest versions which include these enhancements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New sys tables for memory and thread information&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-2275&quot;&gt;DRILL-2275&lt;/a&gt;). Drill includes two new &lt;code&gt;sys&lt;/code&gt; tables that provide real-time metrics about memory utilization and threads on each of the nodes in the cluster. You can run a simple &lt;code&gt;SELECT *&lt;/code&gt; to see what information is available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sql&quot; data-lang=&quot;sql&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;SELECT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;FROM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;drillmemory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;SELECT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;FROM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;drillbitthreads&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support for very wide tables&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DRILL-2739&quot;&gt;DRILL-2739&lt;/a&gt;). Drill previously had some issues with tables that had more than 4095 colums. This limitation has been addressed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now &lt;a href=&quot;/download/&quot;&gt;download Drill 0.9&lt;/a&gt;. As always, you can check out the official &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/release-notes/&quot;&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re gearing up for Drill&amp;#39;s 1.0 release later this month. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Drilling!&lt;br&gt;
Tomer Shiran and Jacques Nadeau&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/05/04/drill-0.9-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/05/04/drill-0.9-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Apache Parquet Graduates to a Top-Level Project</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an exciting day. Apache Parquet, the de-facto standard columnar format for Hadoop, has graduated to an Apache top-level project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Drill project supports a variety of file formats, but Parquet is the highest performing format, and it&amp;#39;s the one we recommend to anyone who wants to maximize the performance of their queries. We&amp;#39;ve had the pleasure of working closely with the Parquet community for over two years, and it&amp;#39;s exciting to see how much the project has evolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ve made a number of contributions to the project, including support for self-describing data. We just implemented off-heap memory management for the Parquet readers and writers, which will improve Parquet&amp;#39;s memory handling. (This enhancement will be available in Parquet 1.8.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to congratulate Twitter&amp;#39;s Julien Le Dem (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/j_&quot;&gt;@j_&lt;/a&gt;), VP of Apache Parquet, and the entire Parquet community on the graduation milestone. Oh, and how can I get a two-letter Twitter handle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Drilling!&lt;br&gt;
Tomer Shiran&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/04/30/apache-parquet-graudates-to-a-top-level-project/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/04/30/apache-parquet-graudates-to-a-top-level-project/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 0.8 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re excited to announce that the community has just released Drill 0.8, which includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?projectId=12313820&amp;amp;version=12328812&quot;&gt;243 resolved JIRAs&lt;/a&gt; and numerous enhancements such as: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bytecode rewriting&lt;/strong&gt;. Drill now leverages code optimization techniques such as bytecode rewriting and inlining to enhance the speed of many queries by reducing overall memory usage and CPU instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced partition pruning&lt;/strong&gt;. Drill can now prune partitions based on arbitrarily complex expressions. For example, specify &lt;code&gt;WHERE dir0 LIKE &amp;#39;2015-%&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt; and your query will look inside the directory &amp;quot;2015-01&amp;quot; but not inside &amp;quot;2014-12&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-time query diagnostics&lt;/strong&gt;. You can now see exactly what your queries are doing in real-time, making it easy to troubleshoot, optimize and manage execution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large records, large # of files&lt;/strong&gt;. Drill was previously limited to small records of up to 128KB. It now supports records of any size. In addition, query performance has been improved when dealing with large numbers of files thanks to a variety of optimizations such as parallel metadata reads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More SQL&lt;/strong&gt;. Drill now features complete support for &lt;code&gt;UNION ALL&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;COUNT(DISTINCT)&lt;/code&gt;. Drill 0.8 also includes new functions such as &lt;code&gt;unix_timestamp&lt;/code&gt; and the window functions &lt;code&gt;sum&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;rank&lt;/code&gt;. Note that these window functions should be considered beta.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better compression&lt;/strong&gt;. Drill can now query compressed JSON files. In addition, the user can control Parquet compression in CTAS (&lt;code&gt;CREATE TABLE AS&lt;/code&gt;) statements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance&lt;/strong&gt;. Drill 0.8 includes broadcast joins, disk-based joins, parallel metadata reads and many other performance-related enhancements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reliability&lt;/strong&gt;. Drill 0.8 includes a variety of fixes that improve the stability of the drillbit daemon, the sqlline shell and the ODBC and JDBC drivers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HBase 0.98 support&lt;/strong&gt;. You can now run SQL queries on any HBase 0.98 table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now &lt;a href=&quot;/download/&quot;&gt;download Drill 0.8&lt;/a&gt;. As always, you may check out the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/DRILL/Release+Notes&quot;&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Drilling!&lt;br&gt;
Tomer Shiran and Jacques Nadeau&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/03/31/drill-0.8-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/03/31/drill-0.8-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MicroStrategy Announces Drill Support</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today MicroStrategy  &lt;a href=&quot;http://ir.microstrategy.com/releasedetail.cfm?ReleaseID=902795&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that it has certified its platform with Apache Drill. According to MicroStrategy&amp;#39;s CTO, Tim Lang, Drill reduces the time-to-value for MicroStrategy users, and enables them to leverage multi-structured data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many early adopters of Drill have been interested in leveraging MicroStrategy&amp;#39;s powerful BI platform. With it&amp;#39;s first-class support for self-describing data and evolving structure, Drill enables MicroStrategy users to explore and analyze the data in Hadoop and NoSQL databases without the usual friction that comes with having to define and manage schemas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to learn more about this integration, &lt;a href=&quot;http://info.microstrategy.com/accessing-multi-structured-data-sources&quot;&gt;sign up&lt;/a&gt; for MicroStrategy&amp;#39;s webinar next month, which includes a live demo of the integration with Drill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Drilling!&lt;br&gt;
Tomer Shiran&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/03/23/microstrategy-announces-drill-support/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/03/23/microstrategy-announces-drill-support/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Schema-free JSON Data Infrastructure</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;JSON has emerged in recent years as the de-facto standard data exchange format. It is being used everywhere. Front-end Web applications use JSON to maintain data and communicate with back-end applications. Web APIs are JSON-based (eg, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.twitter.com/rest/public&quot;&gt;Twitter REST APIs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://developers.marketo.com/documentation/rest/&quot;&gt;Marketo REST APIs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.github.com/v3/&quot;&gt;GitHub API&lt;/a&gt;). It&amp;#39;s the format of choice for public datasets, operational log files and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-is-json-a-convenient-data-exchange-format?&quot;&gt;Why is JSON a Convenient Data Exchange Format?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I won&amp;#39;t dive into the historical roots of JSON (JavaScript Object Notation, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON#JavaScript_eval.28.29&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;eval()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, etc.), I do want to highlight several attributes of JSON that make it a convenient data exchange format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JSON is self-describing&lt;/strong&gt;. You can look at a JSON document and understand what it represents. The field names are included in the document. You don&amp;#39;t need an external schema or definition to interpret JSON-encoded data. This makes life easier for anyone who wants to deal with the data, and it also means that a collection of JSON documents represents what many people call a &amp;quot;schema-less dataset&amp;quot; (where structure can evolve, and different records can have different fields).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JSON is simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Other self-describing formats such as XML are much more complicated. A JSON document is made up of arrays and maps (or objects, in JSON terminology), and that&amp;#39;s about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JSON can naturally represent real-world objects&lt;/strong&gt;. Try representing your application&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;Customer&lt;/code&gt; object (with the person&amp;#39;s address, order history, etc.) in a CSV file or a relational database. It&amp;#39;s hard. In fact, ORM systems were invented to help alleviate this issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JSON libraries are available in virtually every programming language&lt;/strong&gt;. Take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.json.org/&quot;&gt;the list of supported languages on JSON.org&lt;/a&gt;. I counted 15 languages that start with the letters A, B or C.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JSON is idiomatic in loosely typed languages&lt;/strong&gt;. Many loosely typed languages, such as Python, Ruby and JavaScript, have data structures that are similar to JSON objects, making it very natural to handle JSON data in those languages. For example, a Python dictionary looks just like a JSON object. This makes it easy for developers to utilize JSON in their applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;json-data-infrastructure&quot;&gt;JSON Data Infrastructure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional data infrastructure, such as relational databases, has some features that make it easier to store and process JSON-encoded data. For example, Oracle has &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/database/121/ADXDB/json.htm&quot;&gt;a JSON data type and a set of functions for handling JSON data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a new class of data infrastructure is providing a much more seamless experience via a full-fledged JSON data model. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drill is a SQL engine in which each record is conceptually a JSON document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elasticsearch is a search engine in which each indexed document is conceptually a JSON document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MongoDB is an operational database in which each record is conceptually a JSON document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These systems view JSON as a data model as opposed to one of many data types, realizing that JSON offers a simple way to represent real-world objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Traditional Infrastructure&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;JSON Infrastructure&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oracle, SQL Server&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Drill, Elasticsearch, MongoDB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tuple&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;JSON document&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variable schema:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to be in the Bay Area tomorrow, please join Gaurav Gupta (VP Product Management, Elasticsearch), Paul Pedersen (Deputy CTO, MongoDB), Robert Greene (Senior Principal Product Manager, Oracle), Sukanta Ganguly (VP Solutions Architecture, Aerospike) and me for a panel moderated by Gartner&amp;#39;s Nick Heudecker on this new world of schema-free JSON. Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/SF-Bay-Areas-Big-Data-Think-Tank/&quot;&gt;The Hive Big Data Think Tank&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2015 00:50:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2015/01/27/schema-free-json-data-infrastructure/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/01/27/schema-free-json-data-infrastructure/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drill 0.7 Released</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m excited to announce that the community has just released Drill 0.7, which includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?projectId=12313820&amp;amp;version=12327473&quot;&gt;228 resolved JIRAs&lt;/a&gt; and numerous enhancements such as: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No dependency on UDP multicast. Drill can now work on EC2, as well as clusters with multiple subnets or multihomed configurations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/DRILL/Partition+Pruning&quot;&gt;Automatic partition pruning&lt;/a&gt; based on directory structures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New nested data functions: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/DRILL/KVGEN+Function&quot;&gt;KVGEN&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/DRILL/FLATTEN+Function&quot;&gt;FLATTEN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast &amp;quot;schema&amp;quot; return. This provides a better experience when using BI tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hive 0.13 Metastore support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved performance for queries on JSON data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now &lt;a href=&quot;/download/&quot;&gt;download Drill 0.7&lt;/a&gt;. As always, you may check out the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/DRILL/Release+Notes&quot;&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you&amp;#39;re interested in understanding more about where we&amp;#39;re heading, check out Tomer&amp;#39;s recent blog post outlining some of the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/12/16/whats-coming-in-2015/&quot;&gt;planned initiatives for 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Drilling!&lt;br&gt;
Jacques Nadeau&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/2014/12/23/drill-0.7-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2014/12/23/drill-0.7-released/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
